This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
At Kolide, we know end users are IT
admins most significant untapped
resources and key to solving the most
challenging to fix security issues,
including instructing developers to set
passphrases on unencrypted SSH keys,
finding plain text two-factor backup
codes, and teaching end users how to
store them securely, convincing
employees to uninstall evil browser
extensions that may sell their browser
history.
Visit kolide.com/seradio
to sign up today. That's k o l i d e
.com/seradio.
Enter your email when prompted to
receive your free Kolide gift bundle
after trial activation.
You can try Kolide with all its features
on an unlimited number of devices for
free for 14 days. No credit card
required. Try it out at
kolide.com/seradio.
This is Philip Winston with Software
Engineering Radio. Today, my guest is
Dr. Richard Sites. Dr. Sites has spent
most of his career at the boundary
between hardware and software with a
particular interest in CPU software
performance interactions. His past work
includes VAX microcode, DEC Alpha
co-architect, and inventing the hardware
performance counters you see in many
CPUs today.
He has done low-overhead microcode and
software tracing at DEC, Adobe, Google,
and Tesla.
Dr. Sites earned his PhD at Stanford in
1974. He holds 66 patents and is a
member of the US National Academy of
Engineering.
Let's start at the top. What are
software dynamics and what benefits are
there in striving to understand them?
Well, software dynamics refers to
different programs or different threads
of a single program or the operating
system all interacting with each other.
The contrast would be with static
software, a program that you start and
it runs and it finishes. And each time
you do run it, it does sort of the same
thing at about the same speed.
Like benchmarks.
But real software
more and more today is time sensitive
and has lots of user-facing work to be
done or responses to give. And that
dynamically
ends up interacting with all the other
things running on our computer, not just
stand-alone like a benchmark. So, if you
look at something like Activity Monitor
or top or task manager, depending on
your operating system, you'll find
there's like 300 different programs
running.
So, software dynamics refers to the
interactions between all of these in
trying to get responses back to
something that's time sensitive, a
person or a robot or something in motion
that needs responses quite quickly.
When did you first become interested in
software dynamics? Was there a
particular project or problem you can
recall that set you off in this
direction?
That's a good question. When I was at
Digital Equipment,
I got interested in careful tracing of
what was going on in a single program.
And that turned into being able to trace
what was going on in an operating
system, in this case the VMS operating
system.
And one of the questions that the VMS
designers had was sometimes the
operating system would not respond to an
interrupt very quickly at all. It
appeared to be out to lunch for a while.
So, by doing microcode-based tracing of
all of the instructions being executed,
I got to find it. When that happened,
the swapper program had just started up
and was holding on to the CPU and not
taking any interrupts.
And that was a real simple thing to fix
once they knew what the dynamics were,
but they'd never been able to observe it
before.
So, that was around 1980,
1981.
So, do you feel that early software
engineers, say in the 1970s, knew more
about hardware than engineers typically
know today?
Oh, certainly. In the '70s, lots of
people wrote in assembly language.
Compilers optimizing compilers weren't
very good. And so, anyone who paid much
attention to performance had to know a
lot about what the real machine was.
But, it was also a much simpler
environment. We're simply looking at
really running just one program at a
time.
So, who is the target audience for the
book? There's sort of two target
audiences. One is graduate students
interested in software performance, and
the other software professionals who are
actively writing complex software, for
instance, at places like Google or
Facebook or Amazon that have lots of
interactions with
people or with machinery.
So, I'm curious, performance is
obviously a major concern with
understanding these dynamics, but are
there any other goals that might lead us
to want to understand this runtime
behavior in detail? Is it strictly
performance?
To my mind, it is. I mean, that's what
the book is about.
The industry is has lots of
tools, observation tools in software and
hardware help to understand the average
performance of simple programs.
And almost no tools to understand what
delays are when you care about response
time and you have 30 or 40 different
programs running. So, I've tried to look
at the harder problem of understanding
the the
in a very complex environment. Which is
also the environment you would find in
simple embedded controllers.
The embedded controller for Tesla
autopilot has about 75 different
programs running at once and it has
responses that it needs to make
essentially every video frame.
So, I remember the difference between
the average case and I guess maybe not
the worst case, but the you mentioned
the tail latency typically is one
measurement to find these slower cases.
Can you explain a little bit more about
what tail latency is?
Sure. If you have something like a piece
of a program that's responding to
requests for email messages from users
all over the world and a user is sitting
there and says, "I want to look at my
next message." and it pops up. "I want
to look at my next message." it pops up.
"I want to look at my next message." and
there's a 4-second delay and then it
pops up. I'm interested in that variance
in the things that on occasion are slow
even though the average performance is
very good. Some of those slow responses
are just annoying, but some of them are
life-threatening when you're dealing
with big machinery.
Okay, I think that's a good
introduction. The book is centered
somewhat around what you call the four
fundamental computing resources. I guess
the hardware resources, which are the
CPU, memory, disk, and network. And then
you add locks and maybe queues as
critical software resources.
Before we dive into these, there's a
utility you discuss in the book, which
is available on your GitHub site called
KUtrace. Can you tell me a little bit
about what prompted you to write this
utility? When did you have the idea for
it and just kind of how did it get
developed?
Sure. The idea
came about around 2006 when I was
working at Google and we had
intermittent delays in web search and
finding advertisements to deliver and
all sorts of the software services. And
no one knew why those delays occurred.
So, I decided to build an observation
tool that would show us at least what
was happening in Gmail or in in search
or whatever.
And from my previous experience, I knew
that doing something like tracing every
function call inside the operating
system or tracing every piece of code in
in hundreds of applications, so that
would be much much too slow. Because the
delays occurred usually during the
busiest hour of the day in live data
centers.
They weren't things that we could find
by running offline, by running on canned
test programs and stuff.
So, I came up with the idea of tracing
all of the transitions between user mode
and kernel mode, every operating system
service call, every interrupt, every
fault, every context switch.
And worked with one of the Linux kernel
people at Google to build an
implementation that would trace just
those transitions.
And trace it with very low overhead,
less than 1% of slowdown of the CPU.
Because my experience at Google was that
if you went to the people whose job was
to run the data centers and said I have
this great observation tool that has 10%
overhead, so everything will be 10%
slower. It's a really short
conversation. They just say no.
And if you say it's about 1% overhead,
it's also a short conversation. They
say, "Sure, we can't measure a 1%
difference anyway." And if it's any
number in between, it's a long
conversation, and then the answer's no.
Yeah, that makes a lot of sense. And
what really interested me about these
chapters about Ktap trace is you discuss
in detail basically all of the design
decisions behind what you did. It's
almost like a walk-through of your
thought process and
pretty extensive engineering that had to
go into it. I'm going to get back to
this if we have some time near the end,
but I wanted to touch on all of the the
fundamental resources at least a little
bit first. Sure. So, the first resource
you talk about is CPUs. You have a
chapter where you give a great history
lesson on CPU features. For example, you
mention page virtual memory first
appeared in the 1962 machine, Manchester
Atlas.
Reading all of these descriptions of the
features that seem to be additively
growing on each other, I'm wondering do
CPUs always get more complicated over
time or has the trend ever been
reversed? For example, people claim that
ARM chips today are simpler than x86. Do
you feel that's true that some things do
get simpler?
It
happens in waves that things get more
and more complicated and new
instructions are added and features are
added and then
performance gets too slow or the power
dissipation gets too large or the clock
cycle keeps getting longer and longer.
And then there's sort of a step function
and somebody says, "Oh, well, we can do
things much simpler." John Cocke did
that by inventing RISC machines after
complex instruction set machines just
got slower and slower.
We see, I'm not sure I would say today's
ARMs are what less complicated than x86
just because that architecture,
including the 64-bit version, has grown
and grown and grown.
But we do as an industry go through
simple periodic simplifications. DEC
went through that with the VAX
architecture, which turned out to be big
and slow after a while, and the microVAX
architecture was a subset that could be
implemented more simply and more
cheaply, and that extended the life of
the VAX architecture by several years.
Yeah, I guess people talk about the
pendulum swinging back and forth with
architecture, both hardware and
software. In the book, you explain how
the hardware and the compiler can
subvert your attempts to measure how
long individual instructions take. So,
if I wrote a for loop to do an operation
10,000 times
and timed that loop, what are some less
obvious ways that the compiler or the
hardware might make my timings
inaccurate?
I'm going to give you a little context
first. The the first section of the book
for a graduate class, part of the
purpose is to get a bunch of grad
students who've come from different
backgrounds all on the same page. Some
of them will know a whole lot about
CPUs, some will know about memory or
disk, and after the first 4 weeks,
everyone knows a fair amount about all
of those.
So, the
timing on an instruction, I give them
the exercise of how fast is a single add
instruction. You can read some time
base, which we'll talk about, I'm sure,
and do a whole bunch of adds, read the
time base, and subtract, and divide, and
say, "Oh, here's how long it took." So,
I I lead the students into
lots of mistakes by giving them a
program that does this. It's you know,
it's a little short 20 20-line kind of
program, but it has a few flaws. If you
compile it unoptimized and run it, you
get some number like six or 10 cycles
per add instruction. And if you compile
it optimized and run it, you get some
number like zero cycles per add
instruction. And the reason is that in
the optimized form, the GCC compiler or
most any other optimizing compiler takes
out the entire loop because the result
of all the adds is not used anywhere.
And that's sort of leading the reader
into the idea that you need to
be careful that what you think you're
measuring is what you're actually
measuring.
Yeah, I've run into that myself trying
to time instructions and I think I went
down that road of feeling like I needed
to print out some final sum or something
to tell the compiler that I actually
needed that result. And there's a number
of other pitfalls and and tricks you
cover. When I started my career, CPUs
always ran at a fixed frequency. Today,
it seems like the clock frequency can
vary dramatically over time. What
challenges does this pose for timing or
tracing operations? And do real CPUs in
data centers do the frequency is it
variable or do they tend to lock it down
to something?
Varying the clock frequency is a
technique for reducing power consumption
and therefore heat generation. I think
it first started with Intel's SpeedStep
in the
80s. Um
one of the things that gets everybody
used when you're doing careful
performance measurements is some time
base that counts fairly quickly, a cycle
counter. The 1976 Cray 1 computer had a
cycle counter that simply incremented
once every cycle and it was a 64-bit
register. You could read it and you
could literally read the cycle counter,
read it a second time and subtract and
you would get a difference of one, one
cycle.
So, when we did the Alpha architecture
at DEC in 1992,
I included a cycle counter in the
architecture so that any program could
read it.
And a year or two later, cycle counters
started showing up all across the
industry and they would count each time
that the CPU executed, did a clock cycle
to execute instructions. And then a a
few years later, when SpeedStep came
along, the effect was that when the CPU
clock was slowed down to save power,
the time for one cycle slowed down.
And if you're using cycle counter to
measure wall clock time, suddenly it got
way out of whack compared to wall clock
time.
And that matters, for instance, in the
early Google file system, GFS.
The
cycle counter was used along with a
multiply and an add to reconstruct the
time of day, and that was used to
timestamp files. And if you ran on a
machine where time appeared to go
backwards, the file system would crash.
And the effect when SpeedStep came in
was that they could not use it. They had
to keep running the clock at a constant
rate, otherwise the software would would
get confused and crash.
Subsequent to that, people created the
so-called constant rate cycle counter,
which actually just counts time.
And it counts at the same rate
independent of the power saving.
Typically,
it would count at 100 MHz, increment
once every 10 ns.
And that gives you a much more stable
time base.
Yeah, in my work I've run into the
situation, I think it was the RDTSC
instruction on x86, and you had to also
worry about whether your program had
moved from one CPU to another, and
whether the clocks were synchronized
across CPUs. And I just remember there
was a lot of pitfalls there.
So, that's a little bit about CPUs.
There's a lot more detail in the book,
especially about the history and the
complexity.
So, let's move and talk about memory.
So, the chapter on memory
had a lot of information about caching
and the complexities of caching. The
difference between an algorithm that
fights with the cache versus one that's
very cache aware can be extremely large.
Do you feel this is something a lot of
software could do better? Is cache
awareness something that is often
ignored?
A lot of software is not very sensitive
to the cache behavior, but some
important software is. So, if you're
looking at inner loops of matrix
multiply or something, it makes a huge
difference. If you're looking at the
Linux operating system running, the
operating system code isn't terribly
sensitive to cache behavior, except when
it's doing something like bulk moves of
a bunch of data from one place to
another place.
So, it's sort of a mixed bag. On the
other hand, if you don't know anything
about caches,
and essentially caches are speed-up
mechanism, and they're wonderful when
they work as intended, and when the
software uses them as intended. But, if
you end up, perhaps by mistake, with
software that defeats the cache caching
mechanisms, what happens is your
performance just falls off a cliff.
And that happens all over this industry,
not just with caches. It happens with
networks. If you have magic hardware
that offloads uh TCP packet assembly or
something, maybe that hardware handles
eight different active streams, but if
you have nine, suddenly it the
performance drops by a factor of 100.
So, all of these speed-up mechanisms, as
chips get more complicated and and issue
instructions out of order in five
instructions at a time, they're
wonderful until you step off the edge of
the cliff.
And to know about that, you have to
actually understand a little bit about
what the hardware is doing, so that you
recognize
what you've done to yourself when you
step off the cliff. So, one thing that
interested me was all the different
types of caches, different cache levels,
sizes, associativity.
Is it possible to have an algorithm
that's sort of roughly cache aware,
but it's not tuned to a specific CPU? Is
there sort of a spectrum of cache
awareness?
Yeah, the main thing is to when you're
accessing multiple uses of data to have
them stored near each other.
And if you have some huge amount of
data, you know, hundreds of megabytes,
if you go to access part of it, try to
access other parts nearby rather than
being just totally scattered. That's the
main thing.
A term I've come across is structure of
arrays versus array of structures. And I
guess structure of arrays means what
you're saying, that the same type of
data is sort of packed in without
anything in between. Have you heard that
terminology before?
Not recently. I heard it a lot in the
'70s.
If you have something like six parallel
arrays and you're
going for one item in each of the six,
if they are literally separate arrays,
then you're looking at six different
cache accesses.
If you have an array of elements that
are more than one that are all six
pieces physically together in memory,
then you may be looking at one cache
access or one cache miss. I have a quote
I want to throw in here that's from Don
Knuth that's in the book in chapter two.
The quote is, "People who are more than
casually interested in computers should
have at least some idea of what the
underlying hardware is like. Otherwise,
the programs they write will be pretty
weird."
Yeah, definitely. I think that awareness
of hardware is a huge theme in the book.
Continuing on memory for a little bit is
there was a section about the precharge
cycle of DRAM, row versus column access
of memory. I've definitely witnessed the
impact of cache in my software, but I've
never thought about DRAM access at this
level of detail. Have you seen
issues where these hardware details
affect performance, or is it less
significant than, say, caching?
I've seen instances where it does affect
performance.
DRAMs, dynamic random access memories,
aren't random. The internal
implementation of in the transistors,
if you read some place that's near where
you last read in a particular bank of
RAM, it'll be faster than if you are
always scattered about reading just a
few items here and there.
So, it the effect is is much like
caching. The the DRAM chips internally
cache like 2,000 bytes in one access.
And if you reuse bytes within that, it's
faster than if you go to a completely
different group of 1,000 bytes.
Yeah, I guess the term locality of
access that jumps to mind related to
this.
So, that's a little bit about CPUs and
memory. Let's move on to talking about
disk. So, you have disks as the third
fundamental computing resource. You
include a lot of details about both hard
disks and solid state disks, SSDs. Let's
talk mostly about SSDs here, since
increasingly what people are using
Okay.
in their own machines.
So, like with memory, you discuss
several ways that hardware and low-level
software can subvert your attempt to
make simple measurements.
Can you mention some of the ways here
that would subvert your ability to
measure how long a disk access would
take or a disk read or a disk write?
Or an SSD access? Yeah, I think for an
SSD.
Yeah. When you go access, let's say you
want to read a 4K block off of an SSD,
there's all these mechanisms under the
covers that are  helping
you.
The operating system file system almost
surely has a cache of recently accessed
storage data. And so, you may do a read
and you simply hit in the in the file
cache and never go to the device.
Most SSDs actually have a small RAM
inside static RAM inside the SSD
package.
And they will read from the flash memory
into the RAM and then supply data from
the RAM. This is most useful when you're
writing to buffer up all bunch of writes
and then write them out to the
flash
transistors all at once.
But you may find that you do reads that
go that hit in the RAM that's inside the
solid state drive and don't suffer 10 or
50 or 100 microseconds to get to the
real flash transistors.
So everyone has their finger in the pie
trying to speed things up and
occasionally slow things down.
So reading about the specific electrical
properties of SSDs and again the charge
cycles, I guess I got a little confused
on what is the difference between DRAM
and SSD? Is the underlying technology
totally different? Of course, SSDs keep
their data when the power's off, but
other than that, are there similarities
between the two?
They're really completely different. The
flash transistors can hold the value
that you set in them a one or a zero for
10 years or more. But they wear out if
you write them 100,000 times, they stop
being able to separate ones from zeros.
The amount of charge that's stored
inside the floating transistor degrades
over time.
I'm not sure that fully answered your
question.
Yeah, well that's definitely a a huge
difference. I think that what I really
liked about the book is that it packed
in a lot of the details, the hardware
details that I had come across at
various points in my career, but it
packed them into one section. So even
the in the hard disk drive section I
thought was really interesting to read
about all of those details put together.
I should say one other thing about the
SSDs. when you write an SSD,
the actual write of the flash
transistors
assumes that they've already been set to
all ones, and then you selectively
change some of them to zeros.
And the erase cycle that sets them to
all ones
takes a long time. It takes like 10 to
milliseconds. And most flash chips, when
you are doing an erase cycle, they can't
do anything else. And the effect that a
application programmer can see is if
you're doing writes to an SSD, reads
that are intermixed may be now and then
completely delayed by an extra 10
milliseconds because the chip can't do
any reads while it's doing an erase
cycle. And that really is noticeable in
data center performance and in some
other real-time contexts. Yeah, that's
definitely a super low-level detail. And
I guess when I first started to read the
chapter, I assumed that SSDs were going
to be more or less,
you know, perfect performance compared
to hard disk drives. So, it was pretty
interesting to hear about the they have
their own peculiarities that can
surface.
So, that was CPUs, memory, disk. Let's
move on to network. The networking
chapters talk a lot about remote
procedure calls. When I think of
accessing a resource over the network,
I'm usually thinking about HTTP REST.
Are remote procedure calls something
different, or is REST a type of remote
procedure call?
Remote procedure calls are used to
connect together lots of machines that
are sharing work. They don't show up
much if you just have one computer, or
you have a small number of computers
that don't interact. A remote procedure
call is like a procedure call within a
single program.
You know, where where procedure A calls
procedure B, except that B is running on
a different machine somewhere, typically
in the same room, but sometimes across
the country. And the arguments to that
call are shipped across the network to
the other machine where it runs
procedure B and gets some answer, and
then the answer is shipped back over the
network to the caller procedure A, which
then continues.
And that can be incredibly useful for
having something like a search, a web
search at Google, where the
computer that gets a search from a user
immediately fans it out to 100 other
machines using a remote procedure call
for each of those machines to do a piece
of the work. And those fan it out
actually to another 20 machines each or
something, so there's 2,000 machines.
And then the answers come back and are
merged together across those 2,000
machines to other machines to one
machine, and then an HTML page is put
together and sent to the user all in a
quarter of a second or so. So,
specifically remote procedure call could
be implemented by different networking
technology. You're just using it as kind
of a generic term for any type of call
to a remote machine, or is it are you
specifically talking about a certain
type of No, just any generic call.
And most most of the networking chapter
is about waiting on what the other
machines are doing, or you need to
understand who's waiting when.
And the same could apply to remote
access to files.
You have distributed file system across
many machines.
Okay. I said we're not going to talk too
much about KU trace yet, but in the
chapters about networking, you have a
long section, I think, talking about RPC
IDs and how you need to record those IDs
in order to do
a trace. Can you talk a little bit more
about that because I wasn't totally
clear on how you're able to deduce so
much information from just really short
IDs? Okay. If you look at something like
a disaster that I I didn't work on at
all, the US government's roll out of
signing up for Obamacare,
that was a set of computers that
performed very poorly and were usually
not working, put together by about 30
different companies, none of whom had
any responsibility for the entire works
actually delivering sign-ups to
citizens. But they were all connected
together so that whatever a citizen did
would send messages between lots of
different computers.
And when you're trying to figure out why
some response either doesn't happen at
all or happens very slowly, you need
some way of figuring out which message
relates to which, in this case, a
citizen's request or carriage return or
whatever. And so giving all of the
messages some kind of identifying
number, which keeps changing, you know,
every message has a different number, is
an underpinning that's absolutely
necessary if you
want to do any kind of performance
analysis of where did all the time go.
So it can be just a simple number, you
know, 32-bit number.
I see. Yeah, so you're recording these
on the different machines and that
allows you to trace what work was done
on behalf of that call. Yeah, and the
messages between the machines, each
message includes transmitted over the
network that that particular ID number.
I see. Okay, yeah, that makes sense.
How about this term slop you used in
network communications? It sounds like a
very informal term, but how do you
measure it and
how do you decrease it? Yeah, well, if
you have two machines connected with
something like an Ethernet and machine A
sends a message or request to machine B
and machine B gets that and works on it
and sends an answer back to machine A
and machine gets the answer. And that
whole round trip
takes a long time. So, you're concerned
about understanding what's going on, you
might look at
the time on machine A when it sent the
request, and the time also on machine A
when the response came back. And then go
over to machine B and look at when the
request came in,
and when machine B sent the response.
And maybe on machine A, the whole works
took 200 microseconds. And on machine B,
between the time it got the request and
it sent its answer, there is only 150
milliseconds. Let me do all this in
milliseconds.
So,
the sender sees 200 milliseconds, the
server in this case sees 150
milliseconds, and the question is, where
did the other 50 milliseconds go? That's
the slop. It's the difference between
the elapsed time the caller sees and the
elapsed time the callee sees.
And if the slop is a few microseconds,
that's perfectly normal. And if it's
tens or hundreds of milliseconds,
somebody dropped the ball somewhere.
Maybe within the kernel on the sending
machine of the request, maybe in the
network hardware, maybe in the kernel on
the receiving machine, or maybe the
receiving machine's application program
didn't bother to get around to asking
for the next piece of work. And whenever
there's a delay like that, and you talk
to a bunch of software programmers,
there's always It's real easy to point
It's somebody else's problem. And it's
real hard to figure out where the actual
time went.
So, this might be related. Earlier this
year, I saw Facebook released an
open-source hardware implementation of a
time card that contained a miniature
atomic clock chip. They presumably use
this to keep time synchronized between
servers in their data center.
You go into some detail about how we can
synchronize traces from different
machines if the clock is different, do
you feel that tightly synchronized
clocks aren't necessary? Are they worth
the effort of having customized
software, or can we just deal with the
clocks differing by a certain amount?
I'm not a fan of expensive
high-resolution clock hardware.
Google data centers, for instance, have
GPS receiver on the roof or something,
and then the
GPS time is forwarded via software and
networks within a data center room that
might be an acre or something, forwarded
all the machines.
And some other data center in some other
state has its own GPS receiver, etc. But
if you have only one, it's a single
point of failure. I mean, suddenly the
whole building doesn't know what time it
is.
So, in fact, you need like three of
them, and then you need to figure out
which one to actually believe if they're
different.
And
there's also places like Facebook or
papers from Stanford about very, very
careful hardware that can keep clocks on
different CPU boxes synchronized within
a few nanoseconds of each other. And
for
understanding the dynamics of
application software, I found all that
to be unnecessary.
That it's good enough to simply use
whatever 100 MHz kind of cycle counter
clock there is on one machine and and
whatever one there is on another
machine, and they'll differ, you know,
maybe by the time of day might differ by
10 ms or so. And it might drift so that
after an hour it differs by 11 ms.
But if you have time-stamped
interactions between those machines,
and you have some that don't have big
delays, big delays are uncommon in
individual
round-trip interactions, then you can,
in software, from a whole bunch of
timestamps, you can align the clocks
between the two machines in order to
make sense of some trace of what was
happening. And you can pretty easily
achieve 5 or 10 microsecond alignment.
So, one of the things I I encourage the
readers to do and and walk them through
is, you don't really need expensive
fancy clock hardware. You can do
perfectly well with different machines
that have slightly different clock
speeds and align them in software.
Yeah, and you did walk through that in
pretty extensive detail and it seemed
like
not incredibly fancy, but it was
definitely using statistics and you
know, algorithms that were maybe more
than someone would come up with just off
the top of their head.
So, those are four major hardware
resources, CPU, memory, disk, and
network. You include locks as I guess
the fifth major resource. Why are
software locks almost as important as
hardware? And do you feel this is new or
this has been changing over time or
would you have always included
locks as a primary resource?
Software locks are used to keep multiple
threads of execution from going through
the same critical section
simultaneously.
If two things go through something like
reserving the code that reserves an an
airplane seat simultaneously, they might
both get the same seat.
So, software locks weren't around in the
1950s,
but they've become really important
these days when you have large machines
doing
lots of different work. You have
operating systems that run
the same operating system image on four
different cores on a single processor
chip. Use There are pieces of the
operating system where you need to be
sure that two different cores aren't
updating some internal data structure
simultaneously. So, there's software
locks all over.
I once did a search through the Google
codebase when I was there. The the whole
code base is searchable, of course,
since search company.
And there were like 135,000 different
locks declared, software locks.
Most of the delay in real-time responses
in that environment is delay waiting on
locks. It's not waiting on all the other
things that the book talks about.
So, yeah, they're important. You also
talk about queues. I assume that queues
are often implemented with a lock. So,
is this just a special case of locks, or
is there anything about queues which
deserves to be focused on as its own
different resource?
I didn't make the context for the
chapter on queues quite clear enough.
I'm
was specifically interested in work that
is done in pieces. A little piece is
done, and then the package of work to be
done is placed on a on a software queue,
and then later some worker program picks
up that piece of work off the queue,
does the next step or next piece of the
work, puts it on a queue for some other
thread, and eventually, after four or
five steps, the work is completed, and
then the results are sent out or or the
response is is done or whatever. So,
queues themselves have some locking at
the very bottom of the design to make
sure that two different things aren't
being put on a single queue
simultaneously.
But, the the chapter on queuing is more
about the next level up of if you have
pieces of work getting queued up, if
they get stuck in the queues too long,
that's the sorts of delay.
You briefly mentioned lock-free
programming, where special CPU
instructions like compare and swap are
used. I felt like a lot was made about
these algorithms a number of years ago,
but lately I've not been reading as
much. Do lock-free algorithms solve all
the problems of locks or what problems
still remain?
They don't remove the need to do locks,
but they can give you some low-level
pieces that
don't have to block and wait as you
would if some other thread is using a
software lock that you need.
They're just instructions that
atomically within a single instruction
move two pieces of data around instead
of just one piece, and they guarantee
that two different CPU cores aren't
moving the same two pieces
simultaneously such that they get
shuffled out of order. So, you feel the
lock-free algorithms Yeah, lock-free
algorithms are important at a very low
level, and the underlying hardware
instructions are in all machines now.
Okay, that makes sense.
So, we've talked about these five
fundamental computing resources, maybe
six if you count queues separately, and
we've talked a little bit about KU
trace. Two other big sections in the
book are about observing and reasoning.
One of your refrains in the book is
asking people to predict what they
expect to find before measuring it. Why
is this prediction step helpful, and
when did you start doing this yourself
or fall into the habit of trying to make
predictions about performance
measurements? See, I'll answer the
second part first. I started making
predictions when I took Don Knuth's
fundamental algorithms class, and we
counted cycles in this fake mix
processor. And if you don't know how
many cycles or how fast or how much time
something should be taking,
then you run some program on some
computer and you get some performance
numbers, and you say, "Okay, that's what
it does." And you have no basis to
question whether that makes any sense.
So, for instance, the half fast is an ad
where I I lead the students into
optimized code that simply deletes the
loop and says an add takes zero cycles.
If you haven't written down ahead of
time that you think an add might take
one cycle, I have students who say, "Oh,
an add takes zero cycles." and turn that
in as the answer on their homework. So,
the point is to first raise a reader's
awareness that you can actually estimate
within a factor of 10 how long things
should take for almost anything.
And then you have a little touchstone
that if you then go some program and
measure it a little bit, if the
measurement you got is wildly different
than your estimate, then there's some
learning to be done. You might learn
that your thought process for the
estimate was way off. You might learn
that the program is way off. You might
learn that it's a little bit of each.
So, I I think it's a really important
professional step for software
programmers who care about performance.
Yeah, I can definitely see that. So, is
this how would you say it's related to
the scientific method? Like making a
hypothesis, doing some tests, looking at
the data. It sounds like as engineers,
we shift into doing a little bit of
science and then shift back into
engineering. Do you see a connection
between the two? Yeah, I think that's
true.
The estimate is a bit like a hypothesis.
If you're looking at some piece of
biology and you think that some protein
has some action, you make that as a
hypothesis and then you try to design
experiments to see. And in this case,
you you make an estimate of speed or
performance and then you see what
happens and then compare.
And
if you tried to do science by having no
hypothesis, you just say, "Let's do a
bunch of experiments and see what
happens, but we have no idea what that
means."
You don't make progress very quickly.
Yeah, I can definitely tell in my own
work sometimes when I'm running against
the limit of what I understand, I'll
sort of get this anticipatory feeling
like, well, at least I'm going to learn
something here with my next task because
it just has to reveal something. Another
mental model from the book that almost
sounds too simple to consider a model,
but actually I think it is helpful, is
you say when your software is running
too slowly, it's either not running or
it's running, but running slowly. Why is
it worth keeping those two as separate
possibilities? And I guess it could be a
combination of the two also.
Oh, they're separate because the way you
fix it is completely different. If you
have a program that's occasionally slow
doing some operation, it could be
because that program is
on the slow instances executing a whole
lot more code. You know, it goes off in
some does some subroutine call you
weren't expecting to happen and that
that that only happens now and then and
it goes off and does a a lot more work.
That's one choice. The second choice is
it's executing exactly the same code as
fast instances, but there's something
interfering with that code somewhere
around the shared hardware, some other
program or the operating system that's
making it run more slowly than normal.
And then the third choice is that it's
not running at all. And as an industry,
we have lots of tools and profilers and
things that pay attention to where the
CPU time is going, but we're very weak
on tools that say, "Oh, you're not
executing at all and here's why."
So, in the case of you're executing more
code than normal, you need to find what
the extra code path is. In the case of
executing the same code, but slowly, you
need to find what other program or piece
of the operating system is interfering
and how is it interfering? Is it
thrashing the cache? Is it taking over
major portions of the CPU that you're
trying to use, is it loading down the
network, whatever. It's only one of five
things. And if you're not running at
all, then you need to go understand why
the program isn't executing, what it is
that it's waiting for, and then go fix
how come the thing it's waiting for took
too long.
So, in some cases you fix the program
you're working on, in some cases you fix
other programs.
Yeah, I think I remember from the book
one of the examples of executing code
that you didn't expect, and it was
actually preparing a debug value or
preparing some information that was then
not even used. And so, the the
investigation was difficult to find this
case, but the solution was actually very
simple in terms of just not doing that
extraneous work. So, I can see how
that's a very different case from it's
executing the exact thing you expect,
but slowly. So, yeah, they're definitely
different. And that was a real example
from Google that took us about a month
to track down why some service would go
out to lunch for a little while, and we
eventually found, "Oh, there's this big
piece of debug code that's running, and
then the results thrown away."
And this this happens in large software.
Nobody's a bad programmer, it just
you end up with things like that after a
while. Yeah, and and so you definitely
feel like you're discovering this these
traits.
So, one thing I enjoyed was you
mentioned the difference between batch
processing or I guess pipeline
processing or data processing versus
user-facing
transactions, and how for instance your
CPU utilization is your ideal CPU
utilization is different in those cases.
Can you speak to
have you dealt with both of those types
of cases, or is one more its software
dynamics more of a concern with one of
those types?
You know, the software dynamics are is
of a concern in time sensitive code.
A lot of our industry focuses on
simple programs that start and run and
stop and they model them with benchmarks
that run on empty machines and the whole
point of the benchmark is you ran it
five times in a particular machine in a
particular configuration, you should get
five answers, five time measurements
that are about the same. And then the
marketing people take over from there.
But that's not a very good model at all
of software that's on the other end of
your cell phone
or in your cell phone where you're
you're waiting for something to happen.
So, programs that run in the background
or run in batch and nobody's waiting on
them particularly strongly. You know,
they can run for a couple hours and it
doesn't matter if it takes 2 hours or 2
and 1/2 hours. That's a very different
environment than I hit carriage return
and I want something to happen on my
screen. In that environment with the
time sensitivity, you never want the
CPUs to be 100% or even 90% or even 80%
busy. While in the benchmarking
environment or the high performance
physics environment where you're doing
lots and lots of matrix calculations,
the goal is to make the CPUs 100% busy.
So, they're very different environments.
Yeah, and that's a distinction I've run
into also. You're either trying to sort
of soak up all of the hardware resources
available or you're trying to reserve
some for
when you need have a spike in usage or
when you need it.
So, you have two neat examples in the
book. One was I think you were just
investigating or you found this
documented. It was a IBM 7010 from 1964
and this was one of the earliest cases
you found of someone using the type of
tracing techniques that you talk about
to investigate a real performance
problem. I assume it was performance.
And then maybe in the next chapter or
later in that chapter you talk about
some of your work investigating a
specific problem with performance in
Gmail in 2006.
So these examples are more than 40 years
apart. What can you say about the
process of investigation that was the
same and and what was different? We
don't have time to talk about the
details of the investigation, but I'm
just interested were you left with
thinking that the process itself has
remained much the same or or has there
has been, you know, wildly different
processes?
I think the processes are surprisingly
similar. I should say a word about
tracing versus other observations. If
you are dealing with problems that are
reproducibly slow, you can go find those
and fix them sort of working offline.
You don't have to deal with a
user-facing real-time environment,
time-sensitive environment. But if you
have
occasional hiccups in time-sensitive
software, you don't know when they're
going to occur.
And if you don't know when they're going
to occur, you need to do is you need to
watch for quite an interval of time. You
need to watch everything that's going on
and then hope that you get some of these
hiccups so you can track down what what
the root cause is and fix it. And so
there's a lot of observation tools that
do logging and profiling and stuff that
sort of merge together a lot of data and
give you some aggregate numbers. And to
really see these anomalous execution
paths, you need to trace everything
that's happening over on the order of a
few minutes. That's hard to do. It's a
particularly hard to do with tiny enough
overhead that you're not just distorting
what you're trying to learn about. And
that difficulty of tracing what's going
on has been the thing that's constant
from the '50s to now.
The IBM 7010 people, they built a whole
box of hardware to watch the program
counter value on some instruction bus
every cycle
for seconds. And it was a one-off pile
of hardware in some place in
some place like Rochester, New York. And
that was the only way they could see
what the programs were really doing. And
the same thing now, it's real hard to
build low enough overhead tracing
software. You get lots of high overhead
tracing software instead. And then you
can't use it in a real-time environment.
Yeah, I'd forgotten they built custom
hardware to observe the machine. Well, I
think we're going to start wrapping up.
Is there any resources you'd like to
point out where people can learn more
about the book or about yourself? And
I'll put any links you mention in the
show notes, so people can look them up
there.
Okay.
The two main places where the book is
available are on the Pearson or
Addison-Wesley website, which is
informit.com.
That website, in addition to selling the
book, has all of the code that goes with
the book and has started to have
reviews.
The other place is Amazon,
which I think is just just now getting
their first shipments of boxes of books.
Okay, that's great. Yeah, and this has
been recorded in December 2021, so
that's what we're talking about. How
about yourself? Any other links to
recommend or resources? No, I'm I'm not
really on social media very much. I'm on
LinkedIn. Okay, I'll definitely add that
to the show notes. Well, thanks so much
for being on the episode. I really
enjoyed reading the book. You have a lot
of great technical detail that we didn't
get into here in the episode, and I
would say that some of the chapters read
somewhat like a mystery or a thriller.
So, it was really interesting to go
through those examples. Do you have
anything else you want to mention?
Yeah, some of the readers may enjoy the
40-plus index entries under screw-ups.
There's a lot of examples of real-world
screw-ups in the book. Yeah, I I
remember those.
Okay, well, thanks a lot. This is Philip
Winston for Software Engineering Radio.
Thanks.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.